I came here to show you
أتيت هنا لأعرض عليكم
the Fotokite.
الـفوتوكايت.
It's a tethered, flying camera.
إنها كاميرا مقيدة وطائرة.
But before I do that, I want to tell you a bit about
وقبل أن أفعل ذلك، أود أن أخبركم قليلًا عن
where it came from, what motivated it.
مصدرها، وما الدافع وراءها.
So I was born in Russia,
إذن فقد ولدت في روسيا،
and three years ago, in 2011,
وقبل ثلاث سنوات، في 2011،
there were the Russian federal elections.
كانت هناك الانتخابات الفيدرالية الروسية.
There were massive irregularities reported,
وتم الإبلاغ عن مخالفات كثيرة،
and people came out to protest,
وخرج الناس للاحتجاج،
which was very unlikely for Russia.
والذي كان أمرًا مستبعدًا جدًا في روسيا.
And no one really knew
ولم يعلم أحد في الحقيقة
how significant these protests were,
كم كانت مهمة هذه الاحتجاجات،
because, for whatever reason,
لأنه، وبغض النظر عن الأسباب،
the world media largely ignored it.
وسائل الإعلام العالمية تجاهلتها بشكل كبير.
Now, there was a group of photographers
الآن، كان هناك مجموعة من المصورين
who kind of flew flying cameras as a hobby —
الذين أرسلوا كاميرات طائرة كنوع من الهواية -
usually photographing things like the Sphinx,
تصور في العادة أشياء كأبي الهول
the Pyramids — who happened to be
والأهرامات -تصادف أن كانت
right around the corner, and they flew a camera
عند ناصية الشارع، وطيروا الكاميرا
and they took some snapshots,
والتقطوا بعض الصور الفوتوغرافية،
some panoramas of this demonstration.
بعض صور البانوراما لهذه المظاهرة.
Just completely independent entity,
كيان مستقل بالكامل،
completely random occurrence,
حادثة عشوائية بالكامل،
and the image, when I saw it, it really struck me.
والصورة، عندما رأيتها، صعقتني حقًا.
Here's one of the panoramas.
هذه أحد صور البانوراما.
So in a single image,
إذن في صورة واحدة،
you can really see the scale of this event —
بإمكانك بالفعل أن ترى نطاق هذا الحدث -
just the number of people,
فقط أعداد الناس،
the colors, the banners.
الألوان، اللافتات.
You just can't consider this insignificant.
ليس بإمكانك أن تعتبر هذا تافهًا.
All in a single image, which was really cool to me.
كل ذلك في صورة واحدة، ما أمتعني حقًا.
And I think, in the future,
وأعتقد أنه في المستقبل،
journalism and many other professions,
فإن الصحافة وغيرها من المهن العديدة،
there are flying cameras already quite commonly out there,
هناك كاميرات طائرة شائعة بالفعل في الخارج،
but I think, you wait a few months, a few years,
ولكني أعتقد، أنه إن انتظرتمن لبضعة أشهر، أو بضع سنوات،
and for many professions, it's really going to be
فإنها ستكون بمثابة متطلب
a requirement.
للعديد من المهن.
And it make sense. It's such a unique perspective.
وهذا شيء يمكن إدراكه. إنها وجهة نظر فريدة.
Nothing really communicates this scale, for example,
لا شيء يوضح هذا النطاق، على سبيل المثال،
in context, in a way that this does.
داخل سياق، بنفس الطريقة التي تفعلها هذه.
But there are a few hurdles, and they are quite basic
ولكن هناك بعض العقبات، وهي بسيطة نوعًا ما
and quite fundamental.
ومهمة نوعًا ما.
One is piloting.
أولها قيادة الطائرة.
So for this image, they flew a camera,
فبالنسبة لهذه الصورة، قاموا بالتحليق بالكاميرا،
a five kilogram device with an SLR under it.
جهاز وزنه خمسة كيلوجرام مع كاميرا عاكسة مفردة العدسة تحته.
It's quite heavy, lots of spinning, sharp things.
إنه ثقيل نوعًا ما، الكثير من الانحناءات، أشياء حادة.
It's a bit uncomfortable to fly,
إنه شيء تطييره ليس مريحًا إلى حد ما،
probably also for the operator.
ربما أيضًا بسبب المشغّل.
In fact, you can see that on the back of the pilot's shirt, it says,
في الحقيقة، بإمكانكم أن تروا ذلك في خلفية قميص الطيار، مكتوب عليها،
"No questions until landing"
"لا أسئلة حتى الهبوط"
in Russian and in English,
باللغتين الروسية والإنجليزية،
because people are curious, and they'll go tap you,
لأن الناس فضوليون، وسوف يتبعونك،
and then you lose your focus and things happen.
ثم ستفقد تركيزك وربما تحدث أشياء أخرى.
And these guys are great. They're professionals;
وهؤلاء الشباب رائعون. هم محترفون؛
they're really careful in what they do.
هم حذرون جدًا فيما يفعلونه.
So in the protests, maybe you noticed,
إذن في الاحتجاجات، ربما لاحظتم،
they flew over the river so it was quite safe.
طارت الكاميرات فوق النهر فكانت نوعًا ما آمنة.
But this doesn't necessarily apply to
ولكن هذا لا ينطبق بالضرورة على
all people and all conditions,
كافة الناس وجميع الظروف،
so we really have to make piloting easier.
لذا علينا أن نجعل التحليق أسهل.
The other problem is regulations,
المشكلة الأخرى هي القوانين،
or rather, the lack of good regulation.
أو بالأصح، نقص القوانين الجيدة.
For many good reasons, it's just difficult
للكثير من الأسباب الجيدة، فإنه من الصعب
to come up with common sense laws
الإتيان بقوانين راشدة،
to regulate flying cameras.
لتنظيم أمر الكاميرات الطائرة.
So we already have cameras.
إذن نحن بالفعل نمتلك كاميرات.
Everyone here, I'm sure, has a smartphone with a camera, right?
أنا متأكد أن كل شخص هنا، يمتلك هاتفًا ذكيًا بكاميرا، صحيح؟
There are more and more of them.
هناك الكثير والكثير منها.
You hear about people with Google Glass being attacked.
تسمعون بالتهجم على أشخاص يمتلكون نظارة جوجل.
You hear about, actually, a drone pilot,
تسمعون، في الحقيقة، كيف أنه تمت مهاجمة أحد الهواة،
a hobbyist, was attacked two weeks ago
من طياري الطائرات بدون طيار قبل أسبوعين
because he was flying near a beach.
لأنه كان يطيّر واحدة قرب الشاطئ.
Here's some personal input I didn't expect.
هذه بعض المساهمات الشخصية التي لم أتوقعها.
Just yesterday, I was attacked by a guy
البارحة بالضبط، قام شاب بالتهجم عليّ
who claimed that I was filming him.
مدعيًا أنني كنت أقوم بتصويره.
I was checking my email right here —
كنت أتفقد بريدي الإلكتروني هنا -
easy way to get input for your talk.
طريقة سهلة للحصول على المساهمات من أجل الحديث إليكم.
But I think there are better solutions.
ولكنني أعتقد أن هناك حلول أفضل.
I think we have to defuse the situation.
أعتقد أنه علينا تهدئة الوضع.
We have to come up with responsible solutions
علينا أن نأتي بحلول معقولة
that address the privacy issues
تعالج مشاكل الخصوصية
and the safety, accountability issues
والأمان ومشاكل المساءلة
but still give us that perspective.
ولكن توفر لنا أيضًا وجهة النظر تلك.
And this is one potential solution.
وهذه واحدة من الحلول الممكنة.
So this is the Fotokite.
هذه هي الفوتوكايت.
Well, let me see, it's a quadrocopter,
حسنًا، دعوني أرى، إنها طوافة متعددة المراوح،
but what's kind of special about it is there's a leash.
ولكن المميز بشأنها أن هناك رباط.
It's literally a dog leash. It's very convenient.
إنه حرفيًا رباط كلب. إنه مريح جدًا.
And the neat thing about it is,
والرائع بهذا الخصوص هو أنه،
to fly it, there's no joysticks, nothing like this.
لتطييرها، ليس هناك عصا تحكم ألعاب، لا شيء كذلك.
You just turn it on
عليك فقط أن تشغلها
and you point in the direction that you want to fly.
وتؤشر بالاتجاه الذي تود أن تحلق فيه.
You give it a little twist.
تعطيها انعطافًا قليلًا.
That's kind of the way you communicate.
ذلك نوع من طرق الاتصال.
And there it goes.
وها هي تطير.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So the interaction is super simple.
إذن فإن التفاعل بسيط جدًا.
It's like a personal flying pet.
إنها كحيوان أليف شخصي طائر.
It just always maintains a certain angle to you,
إنها فقط توفر لك زاوية معينة،
and if I move around with it,
وإذا تجولت معها،
it'll actually follow me naturally.
فهي في الحقيقة ستلحقني بصورة طبيعية.
And of course, we can build on top of this.
وبالتأكيد، بإمكاننا التطوير عليها.
So this leash has some additional electronics.
يمتلك هذا المقود بعض الإضافات الإلكترونية.
You can turn it on.
بإمكانك أن تشغلها.
And now, it's like telling your dog to fly lower,
والآن، إنها كأن تخبر كلبك بأن يحلق بمستوى منخفض،
if you have such a dog. So, I can press a button
إن كان لديك كلب مشابه، إذن، أستطيع ضغط زر
and manipulate it rather easily.
والتلاعب بها بشكل أسهل على الأحرى.
So I just shifted its position.
إذن فأنا الآن غيرت مكانها.
And it's really safe.
وإنها آمنة بالفعل.
I don't know about you guys in the front row —
لا أعلم ماذا عنكم أيها الشباب في الصف الأول -
(Laughter) — but at least in principle,
(ضحك) - ولكن على الأقل مبدئيًا،
you have to agree that you feel safer
عليك أن توافق بأنك تشعر بأمان أكثر
because there is a physical connection.
لأن هناك اتصالا حسيا.
Live demos are hard, right?
المعاينة المباشرة صعبة، أليس كذلك؟
Things go wrong all the time.
لا تسير الأمور على ما يرام طيلة الوقت.
But no matter what,
ولكن على أية حال،
this thing will actually prevent this thing
في الحقيقة هذا الشيء سيمنع ذلك الشيء
from going into you.
من الدخول عليكم.
What's more, it tells you immediately that
بالإضافة إلى ذلك، فإنها تخبركم فورًا
I am the one responsible for this device.
بأنني الشخص المسؤول عن هذا الجهاز.
You don't have to look for someone controlling it.
ليس عليك البحث عمن يتحكم بها.
Now, I can tell you that it's easy a lot,
الآن، بإمكاني أن أؤكد لكم بأنه سهل جدًا،
but I think a really good way to prove that
ولكني أعتقد أن الوسيلة الجيدة حقًا لإثبات ذلك
is to grab a second one
هو أخذ واحدة أخرى
and launch it.
وتطييرها.
And if I can do this on stage live,
وإذا استطعت فعل ذلك بشكل مباشر على المنصة،
then I can show each and every one of you
عندها أستطيع أن أريكم جميعًا
in five minutes how to operate one of these devices.
في خمس دقائق كيف تشغلون واحدة من هذه الأجهزة.
So now we have two eyes in the sky. (Applause)
إذن لدينا الآن عينان في السماء. (تصفيق)
And now the trick is getting them back.
والآن البراعة تكمن في إعادتهما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So my question now to you is,
إذن سؤالي لكم هو،
well, it's a nice solution,
حسنًا، إنه حل جميل،
it's very accessible, it's safe.
إنه متقبل جدًا وآمن.
What would you use it for?
ما الذي ستستخدمها من أجله؟
What would you use such a camera for in your life?
ما الهدف الذي ستستخدم مثل هذه الكاميرا لأجله في حياتك؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)